so in this section we're going to create
the Friends app which is a basic
contacts application that actually
stores data in the database now the
friends app will allow contact details
to be added edited and that will also
provide a way to search for individual
contacts in the database and although
this is fairly simple app this section
will introduce you to quite a few
important concepts and also methods as
well we're really trying to sort of ramp
up your speed and experience going to
start off with a discussion of databases
and we'll have a look at the databases
that are included with android
specifically SQLITE now when
using databases in an app
there are several different approaches
that can actually be used and generally
you have to assume that database access
will be quite slow so android provides
loader classes that can be used to
prevent your app from appearing to be
or appearing to hang while data is fetched
from the database and in addition to
this i'm also going to talk about cursors
and will actually use cursors in the
Friends app we've seen adapters we've use
those with the list view and recycler view
where they got their data from an
arraylist so in this section we'll also
see how to provide data to an adapter
but in this case the data is going to be
coming from a database and we'll also
see how all of this will fit into the picture to
prevent blocking the UI thread while
retrieving data from a database and this
is also good app to introduce the use of
fragments which are a good way to create
more versatile user interfaces and they also allow us to make better use of the
bigger screen on a tablet for example
while still providing the full features
on a smaller phone screen so a lot to
cover in this section let's make a start